they're so continuing the process with
this episode I will be trying to take a
an extension on the medium post called
understanding the blue church so this is
an effort to see if the visual medium
can help extend or enhance that
particular medium post I don't actually
know whether or not it would be more
beneficial for someone to have read that
first to watch this and agreed it or
community watch this or possible to
engaged in either so here's the the
proposition when I when I used the
phrase or the concepts the blue church
there's a handful of distinctions that I
feel are important to make first that I
noticed the lack of them I think seem to
leave some people confused so first and
foremost I am not in any normal sense
talking about anything like a church
we're not we're not talking about the
Catholic Church or the Episcopalian
Church or big buildings with crosses on
top and whatnot and it is a metaphor and
I think it's a useful metaphor because
there are church things involved with
this this object the blue church a
second while while it is the case that
you can identify certain actual things
like say Harvard or the New York Times
that are part of something that could be
called the blue church I think it's
actually much more interesting important
and useful to perceive this thing this
thing I'm calling the blue church from
the perspective of an abstraction from
the perspective of a fundamental way of
going about doing certain kinds of
things in social space that was
developed in a certain time frame that
I'll talk about in a moment under
certain conditions and that happens to
have been embodied in certain
institutions that we can physically
touch or at least talk about but they're
not actually the key so for example I
would say that there is
some variant on the blue church in most
of the Western civilization's and they
are different institutional structures
and in fact behave differently because
they have different paths dependency on
how they got here so the second
distinction is to try to separate the
the things that we are familiar with
from what I think is the more
fundamental characteristics of how this
particular process came to be and how it
operates and then the third is to make a
distinction between the form the blue
church and the content what I called the
blue faith now again it is the case that
there is a linkage which is why it's
useful to even talk about them both as
being blue between the blue faith and
the blue Church and the color blue
because both are broadly right now in
the United States associated with the
left and with the Democratic Party but
all of those Canon and should be also
decomposed and separated so isolating
the blue faith from the blue church I
think is useful and helpful and I
haven't actually spent an enormous
amount of time digging into the specific
characteristics of the blue faith and
how it came to be I could sort of broad
brush say that it seems to be showing up
as the consequence of the long
development of a number of different
things that were more or less kind of
categorized as the new left back for six
decades ago and how they come to show up
now but you know that's a broad brush
I'm not talking about that I'm talking
about the form the blue church itself
okay so given that let me let me go
deeper what would I mean the the the big
picture concept is to say that in
society which is to say in human
structures that are much larger than the
kinds of Aboriginal social arrangements
that we developed in you know millions
of years ago hundreds of thousands of
years ago in the kinds of things that
emerged at scale after
the development of agricultural
civilization so societies in societies
we need some way to go about getting
this mass of people to coordinate to be
on the same page to be able to make
choices together and to undertake
actions in a coordinated fashion and
that this way I'm going to call this a
social control structure and I don't
mean anything particularly malevolent
about that I don't mean control in the
sense necessarily of tyranny although it
certainly can be tyrannical but more in
the cybernetic sense or even in the
steam engine sense and it's just a
necessary mechanism to get a bunch of
disparate kinds of elements to work
together well and that these social
control structures evolve or develop
under certain kinds of social conditions
so for example the Victorian era social
control structure grew up in the middle
of the nineteenth century under the
context of the significant increase in
population that had been delivered by
the that particular agricultural
revolution but the new urbanization by
the emergence of industrial technology
and by the changes in human mobilization
that were brought about by the railroad
and by the early emergence of the
Telegraph which changed the way that we
could communicate and of course even the
newspaper which also changed the way we
communicate so these are all
characteristics of the social
environment that gave rise to certain
possibilities and certain necessities
that any social control structure would
have to deal with and over time as
certain experiments were tried and
different approaches were endeavoured a
particular collection that I would call
the the Victorian era structure came
into being and it worked for a while and
then in the early part of the 20th
century the situation had changed and
that particular control structure broke
down and we saw in the middle of the
20th century the emergence of a new
social control structure and that is
what I'm calling the blue church so here
we saw again
to change across the entire social field
again a massive increase in population a
significant shift in the way that people
lived the suburban diaspora for example
massive changes in transportation the
ability to travel by aircraft or car
really changed the cosmopolitanism of
individual human beings and the
massification of both production
processes and I think most importantly
Communications so the emergence of mass
media most notably television and so we
might say that the blue church is the
consequence of what happens when you
endeavor to generate a social control
structure in that context and
specifically we might say that the blue
church is how one goes about doing
social control in the context of
broadcast so now I'm making a bit of a
shift and I'm focusing on what I think
is the main point the blue church is
quite characteristically broadcast and
you might even say the broadcast will
tend to show up as something like the
blue church so what does that mean so
first broadcast is a mode of
communication where you have a strong
asymmetry between the signaler the
communicator the expressor and the
audience meaning both that there may be
a small number of signalers like say one
and a potentially very large number of
audience maybe everyone you think radio
or television where one television show
like say the Super Bowl might have
hundreds of millions of viewers and only
a very small number people who are
actually in charge of what's being
broadcast it also has a singular
direction which is that the signal goes
from the signal or to the receiver and
there's very very little going back it
was largely one-way so the mental image
of broadcast television works and it's
important but it's not exclusive you
know if you take a look at for example
the way that the education system at
least in United States shows up in that
same time frame it is also a broadcast
you
a professor who sits at the front
there's only one or maybe two there's a
some large number of students and the
professor is in charge of speaking and
the students are responsible for
listening and there's very little
back-channel and so still a broadcast
typology and the proposition that I'm
making is that this this nature of
broadcast typology one is characteristic
up and down across the blue church and
therefore it becomes one of the primary
characteristics to look at and to has
implications it has implications in
terms of what kinds of things are said
how power shows up and plays with the
constraints of how broadcast operates
and also in terms of what the underlying
consciousness and psychological
characteristics of human beings are that
happen to develop in this environment so
we'll get to that actually in a little
bit and remember this is not a effort to
disparage either broadcast or the blue
church is a diagnosis to describe
something that seems to have simply been
the case a phenomenon and in fact it it
worked really well right we take a look
at the at the scope of what civilization
was able to accomplish in the 20th
century it was broadly astoundingly
awesome the growth the well-being of
human beings went up enormous lead
across the board in almost every
location of there all kinds of
travesties as well for sure but that's
just part of what happened but the
things like being able to go to the moon
or build health care systems that
radically improves the quality of life
were the the Agricultural Revolution of
that century we're all part and parcel
the kinds of things the blue church
could do and it did this by generating a
certain topology so now we're into the
second major point the the topology of
the blue church seems to be defined by
two major characteristics one
characteristic is its organization into
a hierarchy as all broadcasts or want to
be even if it's just a two layer
hierarchy the broadcaster and the signal
but in this case it's a multi layer
hierarchy and it's a hierarchy the
vertical direction you could say
is a hierarchy of expertise or of
legitimate and/or credible Authority so
when it works well the way the blue
church operates is that in endeavors to
put into place various meritocratic
filtering mechanisms to identify
individuals and groups of individuals
who have the capacity for or have
achieved a particular domain expertise
puts them in charge of figuring stuff
out to of making sense of the world and
then of expressing that sense in the
broadcast channels and so you would like
to have the people who know what's going
on being the ones who evaluate what's
happening and then sharing that with
everybody else and that's more or less
the design Early's that's the design
intent and it kind of works well in
certain circumstances and under certain
constraints of course it has a number of
relatively obvious failure conditions
that will always show up in any kind of
asymmetric hierarchy so it's obvious
that if you want to control something
what you do is you find out the control
system and if that control system
happens to have a directionality to the
way that information flows and it tends
to have a hierarchy then what you do is
find a way to get to the top of the
hierarchy effectively created a really
high quality niche and is there any
evolutionary theorists who tell you
every nation is going to be filled and
of course that sort of thing has
happened and will continue to happen in
anything that looks like that now if you
go in the downward direction you have a
different set of characteristics so it's
expertise and legitimate Authority on
what happened all the way up on the way
down what you have is the ability to be
good at receiving and acting on
quote/unquote good opinion so the idea
here is think about the student the the
professor expresses what is to be the
case the the lesson the students job is
to listen to understand to map the
meaningful components of the lesson and
then to be able to respond effectively
to queries the content that's in the
lesson so if you things like a math
class if the teacher says two plus two
equals four the students job is to hear
what is two plus two and respond with
four so this is good opinion
and we can say by the way that this is
characteristic of the totality of
content this is part of the reason why
the blue church is an effective control
structure you know it's very if you
imagined every single human being had
their own bespoke interpretation of how
to drive and what various kinds of
signals like red lights meant you'd have
catastrophe it's actually quite useful
and necessary for us all to be on the
same page about how to respond to
certain signals so that we can
coordinate social behavior and again
that's the idea so within a certain
boundary conditions the idea is the blue
church enables us to have people who
spend time and effort and build
capability i processing what we were
perceiving in reality like say what's
the temperature of the the melting point
of metal and then broadcasting that down
to whoever needs to receive that
information who then receives it and
conveys it accurately and what's
interesting is that is the good opinion
works both in relationship to up and
side-to-side so that we can police and
signal each other simply which is just
that if I express something within the
boundary conditions of good opinion then
at a minimum you can know that I'm part
of your structure you can you can know
that I'm in your group and in fact
depending on the flavor of good opinion
that I express you can even position me
and know where I am in that group and
can orient yourself and how to relate to
me by the way
and even how to relate to me is
oftentimes the content of broadcast okay
so if you watch for example a lot of the
the primary signaling organisms of the
blue church like so the New York Times
most of what they are doing is orienting
the audience on how to orient themselves
towards other phenomena in the world
right they're not actually conveying
content most of the time most of what
they're doing is providing kind of a
prefab set of evaluations of here's what
the landscape looks likes and here's how
you watch respond to it so that you are
active within the constraints of good
opinion or and the most positive spin
you're acting under the recommendation
of wise people who've done a good job
digesting this and providing the prefab
way of responding to the world I'm
obviously you one can take a
generous opinion of what they're up to
okay so that's the second major point so
now we're just kind of into the last
part which is a very good way of
understanding what's happening now is
that the conditions are once again
changing and I should note that there's
a singing to be an acceleration that the
duration of the Victorian control
structure was longer maybe twice as long
as the duration of the blue church
control structure and while it's so very
messy to endeavor to project that onto a
specific curve it nonetheless does seem
to be the case that one of the
consequences of the acceleration of
innovation is a reduction in the
duration of these kinds of control
structures so that implies two things
one is that the if the if you say that
the conditions upon which the blue
church were was created and for which it
was adapted are themselves changing then
this is a lot like the changing of Anish
you know if you if you see the you know
the end of the Ice Age means the end of
the woolly mammoth no matter how awesome
the woolly mammoth was in in in the snow
the the end of the broadcast age and the
emergence of a new way of at the very
least making sense of the world and
coordinating our thoughts and actions
portends the end of the blue church no
matter how awesome or not awesome you
think it was so that's one and and then
we can also begin to do some work on
understanding what might be in the
process of emergent okay well what are
the characteristics the contemporary
environment were the things that might
emerge on top of a symmetric and
interactive medium that's how we can
actually be thoughtful about what the
future might look like and then we had a
centerpiece which is that hey maybe in a
process of accelerating change might
maybe be in a circumstance where
whatever is in the process of emerging
might actually be doomed to a rather
brief appearance you know if the blue
church lasted from say I don't know the
1940s 1950s up until
2016 2010 in that range I were only
talking about a 50 60 year time frame so
if the next thing that comes along last
half as long we're talking about
something that in the historical record
is basically just a blip so it's kind of
interesting I don't know if that's the
case but it's intriguing I noticed this
is running pretty long so I'll just drop
a little a coda and this is something
that was also put into the tail end of
the video I'm sorry into the medium post
and that has to do with what might in
fact be a fundamentally problematic
aspect of this entire approach to social
coordination so I mentioned that there
was a moment before these kinds of
social control systems the human
Aboriginal tribe or band level sense of
coordination that was what we did and
how we operated for millions of years
and now we've been operating under a
different mode social control that has
been figuring out how to do things and
competing with itself since you know 15
thousand years ago or so now there's
actually some pretty interesting things
that we can say about the the maximum
bandwidth the maximum amount of
information processing that a
information processing architecture of
the sort that any kind of social control
system must look like for example
anything that is hierarchical at all has
actually a limit on the amount of
information that it can process and
what's interesting about that is that we
may have passed that limit that the
world that we currently live in the
world that exists as a consequence of
the success of the blue church may
actually be more complex than any
hierarchical social control system can
manage at all so it's not just a matter
that things have changed and therefore
we're in store for some meaningfully
significant shift from the blue church
model to some other kind of broadly
comparable model but rather that
something even more fun
has changed and that therefore we
actually are now in the process of
shifting if we make the shift at all to
something that is as different from
civilization as civilization was from
pre civilized tribal tribalism or the
band level of coordination and again we
can talk about some characteristics this
thing whatever it is if it is to survive
at all must be able to cope with
accelerating change exponential
technology for example it must be able
to cope with the ambient complexity of
the total natural environment and it
must be able to cope with the ambient
and recursive complexity of human beings
ourselves the fact that
anthro complexity is different than just
natural complexity and that's it so
twenty minutes I hope this is
interesting